as Mídia NINJA is already a self-organizing network, I'm dedicating myself to another project. It's called Fluxo, which is Portuguese for "stream." It's a journalism studio in São Paulo downtown, where I used livestream to experiment with what I call post-television formats. But I'm also trying to come up with ways to finance independent journalism through a direct relationship with an audience, with an active audience, because now I really want to try to make a living out of my tear gas resolution back then. But there's something more significant here, something that I believe is more important and more crucial than my personal example. I said that livestream could turn the web into a colossal TV network, but I believe it does something else, because after watching people using it, not only to cover things but to express, to organize themselves politically, I believe livestream can turn cyberspace into a global political arena where everyone might have a voice, a proper voice, because livestream takes the monopoly of the broadcast political discourse, of the verbal aspect of the political dialogue out of the mouths of just politicians and political pundits alone, and it empowers the citizen through this direct and non-mediated power of exchanging experiences and dialogue, empowers them to question and to influence authorities in ways in which we are about to see. And I believe it does something else that might be even more important, that the simplicity of the technology can merge objectivity and subjectivity in a very political way, as I see it, because it really helps the audience, the citizen, to see the world through somebody else's eye, so it helps the citizen to put him- or herself in other people's place. And that idea, I think, should be the intention, should be the goal of any good journalism, any good activism, but most of all, any good politics. Thank you very much. It was an honor. (Applause)
como Midia NINJA era ya una red organizada, fue dedicarme a otro proyecto. Se llama Fluxo, que en portugués significa "corriente". Es un estudio periodístico en el centro de São Paulo, donde experimento en directo con lo que yo llamo los formatos post-TV. También trato de encontrar nuevas maneras de financiar el periodismo independiente a través de una relación directa con el público, con un público activo, porque realmente quiero tratar de ganarme la vida a base de mi propuesta. Pero hay algo más importante aquí, algo que creo que es más significativo y decisivo que mi ejemplo personal. Dije que la transmisión en directo podía convertir la red en una gigante cadena televisiva, pero creo que puede hacer algo más, porque después de ver que la gente la usa no solo para informarse, sino para expresarse y organizarse políticamente, puede convertir el ciberespacio en una arena política mundial donde todo el mundo puede tener una voz, una voz que le represente. Porque la transmisión en vivo rompe el monopolio del discurso político, el discurso literal del diálogo político llevándolo más allá de la voz de unos pocos políticos y expertos y dando poder al ciudadano a través de este poder directo e inmediato de intercambio de experiencias y del diálogo, les da poder para cuestionar e influir en las autoridades de maneras que todavía están por ver. Y creo que hace algo más, que es quizás aún más importante, que puede combinar la simplicidad de la tecnología con la objetividad y la subjetividad de una manera muy política, tal como yo lo veo, porque realmente ayuda a la audiencia, al ciudadano, de ver el mundo a través de los ojos de otra persona, por lo que ayuda al ciudadano a ponerse a sí mismo en el lugar de otras personas. Y esa idea, creo, debe ser la intención y el propósito de un periodismo de calidad, el activismo justo pero sobre todo, la política correcta. Muchas gracias. Ha sido un honor. (Aplausos)